现在我们理解了抗碰撞的哈希函数
So now that we understand what collision
resistant hash functions are and we know
我们知道了如何去构建它们，我们已经准备好
去描述非常流行的MAC：HMAC了
how to construct them, we're ready to
describe very popular MAC called HMAC. So
让我再提一下什么是Merkle-Damgard机制
let me remind you what the Merkle-Damgard construction is. Basically we have a
我们有一个小的压缩函数h，根据h
我们构建一个大的哈希函数
small compression function h from which we
build a large hash function, which is
假设压缩函数是抗碰撞的，则大哈希函数也抗碰撞
collision resistant assuming the
compression function is collision resistant.
本节的问题是，我们能否使用大哈希函数
The question we're gonna ask
this segment is can we use the large hash
来直接构建MAC，而不依赖PRF呢？
function to construct a MAC directly
without having to rely on a PRF. So here's
这是第一个想到的点子。假设我给你一个
the first thing that comes to mind.
Suppose I give you a Merkle-Damgard hash
Merkle-Damgard哈希函数，注意到它把长信息
哈希成短的摘要
function so you notice a mapped, it hashes
large messages into small digests and we
我们想把长信息直接转成MAC。首先我们想到
want to convert that directly into a MAC.
The first thing that comes to mind is well
我们为什么不计算MAC密钥联结上
待求MAC的信息后的哈希呢？
why don't we just hash the concatenation
of the MAC key as long with the message
但实际上这是完全不安全的
that we're trying to MAC? It turns out
that this is completely insecure so let me
我问大家，为什么不安全？
ask you, why is this is insecure?
答案是由于它的标准扩展，如果大家回想Merkle-Damgard机制
The answer is the standard extension of that, and if you think back to the
Merkle-Damgard construction, you realize
会发现如果我告诉你一个特定信息的标签，换句话说
that if I tell you the tag of a particular
message, in other words I tell you the
我告诉你在这个点的值。攻击者很容易加上另外一个分组
value at this point. It's very easy for
the attacker to just add another block and
然后再计算一次压缩函数H
then compute one more application of the
compression function H. And now they'll be
现在他们可以获得原信息联结上补齐分组的标签
able to get the tag for the original
message concatenated the padding block,
联结的字W是他们自己加的，因此
concatenated the word W that they added
themselves and as a result this is an
这是个存在性伪造。是的，这是我们得到的
existential forgery. Yes, so basically
this is exactly what we get here. Where
在联结补齐分组之后，攻击者可以联结
after concatenating the padding block, the
attacker can actually concatenate whatever
任何他想要的，他会获得这个组合信息的标签
he wants and he would get the tag on this
combined message. So this is totally
所以这是完全不安全的，我没法告诉大家
有多少产品犯了这个错误
insecure and I cannot tell you how many
products have actually made this mistake
而它们还假设这是个安全的MAC。这个是完全不安全的
where they assumed that this is a secure
MAC. This is completely insecure and
大家永远不要使用它。有一个标准方法
should never ever, ever, ever be used.
Instead there's a standardized method to
可把一个抗碰撞的哈希函数转成一个MAC
convert a collision resistant hash
function to a MAC and that method is
这个标准方法叫做HMAC。特别地，我们可以使用SHA-256
called HMAC. So in particular we could use
the SHA-256 hash function to build
这一哈希函数来构建MAC。输出256位，事实上
this MAC. The output is going to be 256
bits and in fact HMAC is believed to be a
人们相信HMAC是一个伪随机函数，所以
通过SHA-256，我们获得了一个伪随机函数
pseudo-random function, so in fact out of
SHA-256 we get a pseudo-random
输出256位的信息。那么让我展示这个机制
function that outputs 256 bit outputs. So
let me show the construction. Here's the
这是用符号表示的机制，它如下工作：
首先我们取密钥k
construction in symbols and it works as
follows. First we take our key k and we
然后我们在密钥后面联结一个叫做内部密码本ipad的
concatenate what's we call an internal pad
to it, an ipad to it. This makes it into
这使它成为Merkle-Damgard机制的一个分组
one block of the Merkle-Damgard
construction, so for example this would be
比如，对于SHA-256来说将是512位。
我们把得到的分组附在信息M前面，然后求哈希
512 bits in the case of SHA-256. We prepend
this to the message M and then we hash.
我们刚刚说了，只做这些是完全不安全的
Now this by itself we just said is
completely insecure, however what HMAC
不过除此之外，HMAC还取这256位输出
does in addition, it takes the output,
which is 256 bits, it prepends to that the
计算密钥k与外部密码本opad异或，把异或结果
附在256位输出的前面
key again XOR with, what's called the
outer pad, the opad. This also becomes
这也会形成512位，一个分组。然后HMAC取
这两个分组的哈希值
512 bits. It's one block. And then it
hashes the combination of these two to
最终得到信息M的标签。这里符号略多
finally obtain the resulting tag on the
message M. So it's more rather looking
看图更有利于对HMAC的理解
into some symbols. It's more instructive
to look at HMAC in pictures. And so you
大家可以看到这是两个密钥k异或内部密码本
can see that here are the two keys k XOR
inner-pad, which is then fed into the
然后交给Merkle-Damgard机制，得到的输出
Merkle-Damgard chain. And then the
resulting output of this chain is fed into
再交给Merkle-Damgard机制，产生最后的输出
another Merkle-Damgard chain and finally
the final output is produced. Okay, so
这是HMAC工作的示意图，现在我想证明
this is how HMAC works in pictures and
now I want to argue that we've already
一些我们已见过的类似的结果。特别地
seen something very similar to this. In
particular, if you can think of the
如果压缩函数H是PRF，密钥是第一个、上面的输入
compression function H as a PRF where the
key is the first, the top inputs, then
那么我们这里是在计算PRF H在固定的IV处的值
what we're actually doing here is we're
evaluating this PRF H at a fixed IV and
结果是一个随机值，我们记为K1
the result here is a random value which
we're gonna call K1. And then we apply the
然后我们应用Merkle-Damgard链，
对外部密码本我们可以做同样的事情
Merkle-Damgard chain and we can do the
same thing on the outer pad. If you think
如果你认为h是PRF，密钥是上面的输入
of little h as a PRF where the key is the
upper inputs. Again, we're applying this
我们使用不同的密钥，应用这个PRF，计算在固定值IV的值
PRF using a different key to a fixed value
IV and as a result, we're gonna get
我们得到另外一个结果K2。现在当我们
使用这些密钥K1和K2来计算HMAC时
another random value K2. So now when we
compute HMAC using these keys, K1 and K2,
这看上去非常熟悉，这就是NMAC
this would actually look very familiar
this is basically NMAC. It's identical to
它和我们前一章讨论的NMAC一模一样
NMAC that we discussed in a previous
segment. And notice to argue that this is
(口误：segment->module)
为了证明这是NMAC机制，我们必须假设这个压缩函数h
an NMAC construction we have to assume
that the compression function, little h,
是PRF，密钥是下面的函数输入
is a PRF where the key is actually the
lower inputs to the function. Now let me
我说这些密码本ipad和opad，它们是固定的常数
say that these pads, the ipad and the
opad, these are fixed constants that are
在HMAC标准中都给出了。这些仅为512为常数
specified in the HMAC standard. So these
are literally just 512 bit constants that
永不改变。当我们回头看整个HMAC机制时
never change. And so when we go back to
look at the complete HMAC construction,
发现HMAC与NMAC的主要不同之处
you realize that the main difference
between this and NMAC is that these keys
是这些密钥互相是有关联的，大家注意到
它们只不过是同样的密钥
here since they are dependent, you notice
they're both just the same key XORed
异或上不同的常数。本质上，密钥K1和K2也是相互关联的
with different constants. Essentially, the
keys K1 and K2 are also somewhat dependent
因为它们是在同样的固定值IV上应用PRF计算得到的
because they're computed by applying a PRF
to the same fixed value, namely IV, but
但用相关联的密钥。为了证明K1和K2是伪随机的
with dependent keys. And so to argue that
K1 and K2 are pseudo random and
且互相独立的，我们必须证明压缩函数
independent of one another, one has to
argue that the compression function not
不仅当其输入，上面的输入是密钥时，它是PRF
only is a PRF where when the inputs, the
top input, is the key inputs, but it's
而且当使用关联密钥时，它也是PRF。基于这些假设
also a PRF when dependent keys are used.
But under those assumptions, basically the
应用对NMAC的一模一样的分析来分析HMAC，我们可以证明
exact same analysis NMAC would apply to
HMAC and we would get security argument
HMAC是安全的MAC。如我所说，在这些压缩函数h的PRF假设下
that HMAC is a secure MAC. So as I said,
HMAC can be proven secure under these PRF
可以证明HMAC是安全的。其安全的界定
assumptions about the compression function
H. The security bounds are just as they
与NMAC一致，换句话说，你不必改变密钥
are for NMAC, in other words you should
not have to change the key as long as the
只要求MAC的信息数小于输出标签的一半的空间大小
number of messages you're MAC-ing is
smaller than the size of the output tag to
(这样讲有歧义，本质上就是生日攻击里的平方根)
对于HMAC与SHA-256，输出空间是2的256次方
the one-half, but for HMAC SHA-256 the
output space is 2 to the 256. The square
平方根是2的128次方
root of that would put us at 2 to the
128. Which means that basically you can
这意味着你可以使用HMAC与SHA-256，
想处理多少信息都可以，而且是始终保持安全的
use HMAC SHA-256 for as many outputs as you
want, and you'll always maintain security.
最后关于HMAC，我告诉大家，TLS要求
And as a last point about HMAC I'll tell
you that TLS Standard actually requires
支持HMAC与SHA-196，意味着HMAC由SHA-1函数构建
that one support HMAC SHA-196 which means that
HMAC built from the SHA-1 function and
并截断到96位。SHA-1输出160位
truncated to 96 bits. SHA-1 remember
outputs 160 bits. And we truncated to the
我们把它截断到高96位。现在大家可能怀疑，
记得我们之前说过
most significant 96 bits. Now you might be
wondering, remember we said before that
SHA-1不再被认为是安全的哈希函数
SHA-1 is no longer considered a secure
hash function, so how come we're using
那我们怎能在HMAC里使用SHA-1呢？实际上，
这是没问题的，因为HMAC的安全性分析
SHA-1 in HMac? Well, it turns out it's
actually fine. Because HMAC the analysis
不需要SHA-1是抗碰撞的
of HMAC doesn't need SHA-1 to be
collision resistant. All it needs is that
只需要压缩函数SHA-1是PRF，当输入运行是密钥时
the compression function of SHA-1
one be a PRF when either input is allowed
目前我们知道，这对SHA-1的底层压缩函数也成立
to be the key. And as far as we know
that's still correct for the underlying
即使它可能不是抗碰撞的
compression function for SHA-1.
Even though it might not be collision
(单轮Merkle-Damgard一般很难做到抗碰撞)
我们目前知道，在HMAC中使用SHA-1的压缩函数也是没问题的
resistant. As far as we know it's still
fine to use it inside of HMAC. So this is
我们对HMAC的讨论完结。下一节我们看
the end of our discussion of HMAC and in
our next segment we're going to look at
HMAC的计时攻击
timing attacks on HMAC.